Guide to the Department of Athletics, Yale University, Records Documenting Crew
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Department of Athletics, Yale University, records documenting crew
1843-2002
RU 121
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
32.5
The records consist of logbooks, scrapbooks, correspondence, profiles, and ephemera of the Yale crew team. Also included is a memoir of Archie Monroe Quarrier who, as a member of the Yale crew team, participated in the 1924 Olympics in Paris.
Yale University. Dept. of Athletics
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 38-B (YRG 38-B), Records documenting specific sports at Yale.
Existence and Location of Copies
Crew scrapbooks, 1916-1935 are available on microfilm from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM162. 1983 and 1985. 4389 frames on 5 reels, 35mm. Crew logbook, 1881-1905 is available on microfilm from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM163. 1983. 393 frames on 1 reel, 35mm. Logbook of freshman crew, 1893 (along with boat club records) is also available on microfilm (230 frames on 1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM161. Logbook of the Yale crew, 1903-1938 is also available on microfilm (381 frames on 1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM79.
Conditions Governing Access
The records are partially restricted. See inventory for details.
The captain of the crew team is allowed to use the logbooks.
Arrangement
The records are arranged by accession.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of logbooks, scrapbooks, correspondence, profiles, and ephemera of the Yale crew team. Also included is a memoir of Archie Monroe Quarrier who, as a member of the Yale crew team, participated in the 1924 Olympics in Paris.
College sports; Rowing; Scrapbooks; Quarrier, Archie Monroe; Yale University Athletic Association; Yale University -- Rowing; Yale University -- Sports; Yale University. Dept. of Athletics
- Freshmen crew team log, 1890-1892; Accession 19ND-A-369
  - Freshmen crew log, 1890-1892 (Box 1–2)
- Memoir of Archie Monroe Quarrier, 1924; Accession 1984-A-076
  - Memoir of Archie Monroe Quarrier, 1924 (Box 1)
- Men's crew team logbooks and memorabilia, 1958-1986; Accession 1989-A-117
  Conditions Governing Access
  The materials are open for research.
  - Logbooks
    - 1958-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1964-1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Memorabilia, 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Logbooks
    - 1975-1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Memorabilia, 1983-1986 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Records of the men's crew team and boat club, 1913-1951; Accession 1990-A-043
  - Records of the men's crew team and boat club, 1913-1951 (Box 1)
- Men's crew team captain's logbook, 1985-1990; Accession 1994-A-015
  Restricted until Jan 1, 2025
  - Captain's logbook, 1985-1990 (Box 1)
- Men's crew team records, 1925-1972; Accession 1995-A-049
  - Captain's logbook, 1925-1933 (Box 1)
  - Hoyt Pease's records of the Yale-Harvard Regatta committee, 1962-1972 (Box 1)
- Men's crew team captain's logbooks, 1990-1993; Accession 1996-A-029
  Restricted until Jan 1, 2028
  - Captain's logbooks, 1990-1993 (Box 1)
- Men's crew team captain's log book, 1994-1995; Accession 1999-A-078
  Restricted until Jan 1, 2030
  - Captain's log book, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
- Silk banner commemorating the Yale crew team's victory over Harvard, 1907; Accession 2003-A-047
  - Silk banner commemorating the Yale crew team's victory over Harvard, 1907 (Box 1)
- History of the 1952 heavyweight crew team, 1949-1952; Accession 2004-A-056
  - History of the 1952 heavyweight crew team, 1949-1952 (Box 1)
- Highlights from dinner in honor of Yale's Olympic crew team and Ivy League Championship Football team [sound recording], 1957; Accession 2005-A-087
  Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
  - Highlights from dinner in honor of Yale's Olympic crew team and Ivy League Championship Football team held at the Waldorf Astoria, NY, phonodisc (LP), 1957 February 13 (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks of the men's crew team, 1916-1979; Accession 2006-A-040
  Scrapbooks are partially available on microfilm. Patrons must use HM FILM 162 instead of the originals where a microfilm reel number is listed.
  - Scrapbooks
    - 1888 (Box 1)
    - 1916-1921 (Box 1, Reel 1, Box 2)
    - 1921 (Box 3, Reel 1)
    - 1921 (Box 12, Reel 1)
    - 1923-1925 (Box 4, Reel 2, Box 5)
    - 1923-1926 (Box 6, Reel 2)
    - 1926 (Box 7, Reel 2)
    - 1927-1928 (Box 8, Reel 2)
    - 1928-1929 (Box 9, Reel 2)
    - 1929-1930 (Box 10, Reel 2)
    - 1930-1931 (Box 11, Reel 2)
    - 1931-1932 (Box 13, Reel 3)
    - 1932-1934 (Box 14, Reel 3)
    - 1934-1935 (Box 15, Reel 3)
    - 1929-1931, compiled by R.T. Bulkeley (Box 16)
    - 1948-1950, compiled by Karl Heilman (Box 16)
    - 1951-1952, compiled by Karl Heilman (Box 16)
    - The 1956 Yale Olympic Crew: Winning the Gold -the Hard Way, compiled by Karl Heilman (Box 16)
    - 1956 (Box 17, Folder 1 - 2)
    - 1956 (Box 18)
    - 1979 photograph album (Box 18)
- Records of the men's crew team, 1909-1996; Accession 2006-A-231
  Restricted until Jan 1, 2031
  - Men
    - Association, 1980-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Association Improvement, 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1978-1989 (Box 1, Folder 3 - 4)
    - Endowment Correspondence, Lightweight Crew, 1981, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - General, 1928-1939,1981-1991 (Box 1, Folder 6 - 12)
    - History of Yale Crew 1843-1922, by Roy Rom, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Manual, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Payne Whitney Gymnasium, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Photographs, 1909, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Regatta Correspondence, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Regatta Minutes, 1931-1940 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Regatta -Yale-Harvard, 1983,1984 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - San Diego Crew Classics, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Windmere Cup, Seattle Trip, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Travel/Henley Royal Regatta Budget, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 22 - 24)
    - Heavyweight crew (Box 2, Folder 24A)
    - Association correspondence, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Memos, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Squad info, profiles
      - 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Freshmen, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Lightweight crew, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Women
    - Squad info, profiles, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Team info, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Memos, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Women's Crew Association, correspondence, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Publications, 1953-1995 (Box 3, Folder 36-37)
- Logbooks and scrapbooks of the men's crew team, 1843-1938; Accession 2006-A-252
  - Logbooks
    - 1881-1905, microfilm (Reel 1)
    - 1905-1937, microfilm (Reel 2)
    - 1919 (Box 3)
    - 1923 (Box 3)
    - 1927-1931 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbooks
    - 1843-1938, microfilm (Reel 4)
    - 1904-1928, microfilm (Reel 5)
    - 1929-1930, microfilm (Reel 6)
    - 1931-?, microfilm (Reel 7)
- Records documenting the recognition of Mr. Robert J. Cook, 1887; Accession 2019-A-0042
  - Invitation and letter indicating the honoring of Mr. Robert J. Cook for his service to the Yale men's crew team., 1887 (Box 1, Folder 1)